Register of the Boutros Boutros-Ghali papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Boutros Boutros-Ghali papers
1867-2001
96065
Hoover Institution Archives
279 manuscript boxes, 9 videocassette boxes, 1 oversize box, 1 oversize folder (115.0 linear feet)
Speeches and writings, memoirs, correspondence, clippings, and printed matter relating to international law, Egyptian foreign relations, international relations in the Middle East and throughout the world, and activities of the United Nations. Includes some papers of Charles Hill as special adviser to the secretary-general of the United Nations. Also includes photocopies of Boutros-Ghali family papers relating to the history of the Coptic Church.
Boutros-Ghali, Boutros, 1922-2016.
Hill, Charles, 1936-
Boutros-Ghali family.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1996.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Collection(s)
Charles Hill papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Javier Pérez de Cuéllar papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Boutros Boutros-Ghali papers, United Nations Archives
Biographical Note
1922 November 14 Born, Cairo, Egypt
1946 Bachelor of Laws, Cairo University
1949 Ph.D. in international law, University of Paris
1949-1977 Professor of international law and international relations, Cairo University
1960-1975 Editor, Al-Ahram al-Iqtisadi
1963-1964 Director of the Centre of Research of The Hague Academy of International Law
1965 President of the Egyptian Society of International Law
1967-1968 Visiting professor, Faculty of Law, University of Paris
1971-1979 Member of the Committee on the Application of Conventions and Recommendations of the International Labour Organization
1975 President, Centre of Political and Strategic Studies (Al-Ahram)
1977-1991 Minister of State for Foreign Affairs of Egypt
1978 September Helped negotiate Camp David accords between Egypt and Israel
1979 Camp David accords signed Member of the Institute affari internazionali (Rome)
1979-1991 Member of the International Law Commission
May 1991 Appointed Deputy Prime Minister for Foreign Affairs, Egypt
1992-1996 Sixth secretary general of the United Nations
1997 Author, Egypt's Road to Jerusalem: A Diplomat's Story of Struggle for Peace in the Middle East
1999 Author, Unvanquished: A U.S.-U.N. Saga
2016 February 16 Died, Cairo, Egypt
Source: United Nations. Biography of Secretary-General Boutros Boutros-Ghali. http://www.un.org/Overview/SG/sg6bio.html
Scope and Content of Collection
The Boutros Boutros-Ghali papers were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1996, with subsequent increments in the years following. The papers reflect Boutros-Ghali's long career in international politics, in particular his service as minister of state for foreign affairs in Egypt and his term as the sixth secretary general of the United Nations. Included among these records are the papers of Charles Hill, reflecting his role as advisor to Boutros Boutros-Ghali and their joint work at the United Nations. In addition, the collection includes photocopies of the archives of the Boutros-Ghali family, the originals of which reside with the family.
The Boutros-Ghali Family Archive is chronologically the earliest material in the collection. The series is comprised of photocopies of the family's papers, covering a wide range of events and activities relating not only to Egyptian history, but also to the history of Coptic Christians in Egypt and Ethiopia. The series is arranged in its original groups with the original classification scheme retained. Noteworthy among these records are documents relating to Boutros Ghali Pasha's premiership and his assassination in 1910 by an Egyptian nationalist, marking a period of increased clashes between Muslims and Coptic Christians in Egypt. The series also includes unique records on the relationship between the Egyptian and Ethiopian Coptic churches, and Mirrit Boutros-Ghali's role in the negotiations concerning the separation of these churches.
The Correspondence Files are arranged chronologically in groups corresponding to the original arrangement of the materials. The files reflect Boutros-Ghali's career as a professor at Cairo University, editor of Al-Ahram al-Iqtisadi, member of the International Law Commission, as well as his involvement with numerous human rights groups, socialist unions, and other international law organizations.
Boutros-Ghali served as minister of state for foreign affairs of Egypt from 1977, elected under Anwar as-Sadat, until 1991, when he was appointed deputy prime minister by Hosni Mubarak. The Minister of State for Foreign Affairs (Egypt) File is mostly comprised of clippings about Boutros-Ghali, but also contains some of his routine diplomatic correspondence, retained in the original groups. Materials relating to the Senegal-Mauritania conflict are included in this series.
Boutros-Ghali's term as Secretary-General of the United Nations was characterized by numerous global crises, including the dissolution of Yugoslavia, Bosnian genocide, Rwandan genocide, and the famine in Somalia; a reform of the Secretariat; and a changing relationship between the United States and United Nations. A large portion of the series is comprised of publicity materials, including clippings, trips files, and media reports, which provide detailed information on the Secretary-General's public activities. Reflecting more internal activities are the Secretary-General's appointment books, available for every month from 1992 to 1996. In addition to listing who visited the Secretary-General on which day, some of the more important meetings contain minutes or other documentation as well. For example, the May 1993 volume contains minutes of meetings with Canadian Prime Minister Brian Mulroney, U.S. Secretary of State Warren Christopher, French Foreign Minister Alain Juppe, Danish Prime Minister Poul Rasmussen, and Archbishop Desmond Tutu from South Africa, among others.
The speeches and writings in the Secretary-General of the United Nations File are arranged chronologically and include statements Boutros-Ghali made at UN engagements, as well as drafts and research materials for his three major reports as Secretary-General: An Agenda for Peace, An Agenda for Development, and An Agenda for Democratization. Geographical files contain binders of memoranda, correspondence, and other documentation on policy matters for different geographic regions. Noteworthy among these files is correspondence from Libya regarding the Lockerbie bombing and subsequent UN sanctions, as well as records about the Oil for Food program in Iraq.
Because of the collaborative nature of their relationship, some papers of Charles Hill are included in this collection. The Charles Hill Advising and Projects File is comprised not only of records created during his work as policy advisor to the Secretary-General, but also contains records relating to the publication of the three volume Papers of the United Nations Secretary-General, Boutros Boutros-Ghali, published by Yale University Press and compiled and edited by Hill. Memoranda and correspondence exchanged between Jean-Claude Aimé (Mr. Boutros-Ghali's chief of staff) and Hill regarding policy developments, edits to speeches and statements by the Secretary-General, and other related tasks are also included. The series also contains a small amount of material on Hill's work with Gidon Gottlieb on crafting an Israeli-Palestinian peace solution. Other relevant materials may be found in the Charles Hill papers at the Hoover Institution Archives.
Writings by Others includes the original handwritten manuscript of the first history of modern Egypt by Boutros-Ghali's maternal grandfather, Mikhail Sharubim.
Sources: Goldschmidt, Arthur. "Boutros Ghali." Encyclopedia of the Modern Middle East. Gale, 2004. Gale Biography In Context. Web.
Egypt--Foreign relations--1952-; Middle East.; World politics.; International law.; United Nations.; Coptic Church.; Statesmen--Egypt.
- Datebooks, 1981-1985 (Boxes 1-2)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes four datebooks, arranged chronologically.
  - 1981 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - 1982 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - 1983 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - 1985 (Box-folder 2: 1)
- Memoir, 1977-1979 (Boxes 2-5)
  Includes English and Arabic typed memoir of experience negotiating the Camp David accords between Egypt and Israel. See also Speeches and Writings/ Egypt's Road to Jerusalem.
  - Original, 1977-1979; Typescript
    - 1977 October-December (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - 1978 January-December (Box-folder 2: 3-6)
    - 1979 January-October (Box-folder 3: 1-5)
  - Photocopy of original, 1977-1979
    - 1977 October-December (Box-folder 3: 6)
    - 1978 January-February (Box-folder 3: 7)
    - 1978 March-December (Box-folder 4: 1-3)
  - English translation, 1977-1979; Typescript
    - 1977 October-December (Box-folder 4: 4)
    - 1978 January-December (Box-folder 4: 5-8)
    - 1979 January-October (Box-folder 5: 1-5)
- Correspondence Files, 1953-1991 (Boxes 6-18)
  Includes mostly correspondence, but also conference and meeting materials, reports, newsletters, and other printed matter from and about different organizations and universities that Boutros Boutros-Ghali was involved with. In Arabic, French, and English. Arranged chronologically.
  - Hague Academy of International Law correspondence, reports, and meeting materials, 1953-1977 (Box 6)
    Relates mostly to events and activities of the Centre for Studies and Research in International Law and International Relations. Includes some materials from Dag Hammarskjöld Foundation, Sweden and writings of Zarko Ratkovic.
    - "Académie - 2", 1953-1977 (Box-folder 6: 1-4)
    - "Académie - 1", 1962-1965 (Box-folder 6: 5-8)
  - Non-academic organizations, 1954-1977 (Box 7)
    Scope and Content Note
    Correspondents include African Association of Political Science (University of Dar El Salaam); Afro-Asian Organization for Economic Cooperation; Arab Socialist Union Workers Educational Association; Ahmad Salah Bukhari; J. Chlala; Egyptian Association of Political Science, International Law Association in the United Arab Republic; Egyptian Society of International Law; Faculté des sciences juridiques économiques et sociales; Institute of Public Administration United Arab Republic and United Nations; League of Arab States; Middle East Research Center (Ain Shams University); Societé d'archéologie copte; Societé Egyptienne de droit international; Societé Française pour le droit international; Supreme Council for the Welfare of Arts and Letters; UNESCO; and the United Arab Republic-U.S.A. Educational Exchange Commission.
    - 1953-1970 (Box-folder 7: 1-9)
    - 1974-1977 (Box-folder 7: 10-11)
    - 1975-1977 (Box-folder 7: 12)
  - Lettres de l'etranger [letters from abroad], 1955-1979 (Boxes 8-13)
    Scope and Contents Note
    The files contain mostly general correspondence with academic institutions and non-governmental organizations relating to papers submitted for publication, international law and human rights, and academic affairs. Almost all letters are addressed to Boutros-Ghali as economics editor at Al-Ahram or professor at Cairo University. Files also contain some conference schedules, student papers, and newsletters.
    - File 1, 1955-1964 (Box-folder 8: 1-4)
      Correspondents include M. S. Agwani; Morroe Berger; Joseph E. Black; Carnegie Endowment for International Peace (Frances Colville, Francis Deak, John Goormaghtigh, Anne Winslow); C. A. Colliard; G.I.A.D. Draper; René-Jean Dupuy; Gilbert Etienne; Samaan B. Farajallah; Jacques Freymond; Curt Gasteyger; Gustave Edmund von Grunebaum; James J. Halsema; Edvard Hambro; C. Hillem (Netherlands Institute for the Middle East); John C. Hunt (Congrès pour la liberté de la culture); Malcolm Kerr; League of Arab States; Henry Kissinger (Harvard University International Seminar); C.A.O. van Nieuwenhuijze; Francisco Jose Palanca; Jovica Patronogić; Giorgio La Pira; Georges Vedel
    - File 2, 1955-1967 (Box-folder 8: 5-7, Box-folder 9: 1)
      Correspondents include George Abi-Saab; Jean-Jacques Berreby; Joseph E. Black; Carnegie Endowment for International Peace (Anne Winslow, John Goormaghtigh); Georges Carlier; C. Chamass; Eugene Cotran; Michel Cotran; Lawrence Finkelstein; Omar Z. Ghobashy; Tord Hagen; John C. Hunt; J. C. Hurewitz; Judge Philip C. Jessup; Vladimir Kopal; Mateo J. Magariños de Mello; S. E. Nahlik; William R. Polk; Z. M. Quraishi
    - File 2A, 1967-1969 (Box-folder 9: 2-4)
      Includes planning materials and correspondence relating to UNESCO Mission for Zambia and Malawi
    - File 3, 1967-1971 (Box-folder 9: 5-8)
      Relates mainly to publication of Le Mouvement Afro-Asiatique. Correspondents include the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace (Anne Winslow); René-Jean Dupuy; Maurice Flory; Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations; Omar Z. Ghobashy; Edvard Hambro; League of Arab States; H. Michel; Edmond Rabbath; Ignaz Seidl-Hohenveldern
    - File 4, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 10: 1-4)
      Correspondents include Rosemary Abi-Saab; Ariel Foundation (B. J. Hayhoe, T. G. Martin); F. S. Arkhurst; Mohammed Bedjaoui; Morroe Berger; Jesús Contreras Granguillhome; René-Jean Dupuy; Yassin El-Ayouty; Perker T. Hart; J. L. Henderson (World Community Heroes Competition); Farag Moussa; Juan Pekmez; Walter Siegl; UNESCO (Gene M. Lyons); United Nations Institute for Training and Research (Unitar); University of Dar Es Salaam; Francis Wolf (International Lawyer's Club). Also includes Systems of Alliances by Boutros Boutros-Ghali
    - File 5, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 10: 5-6, Box-folder 11: 1-2)
      Correspondents include Zein Ali Ibrahim (University of Khartoum); Sir Richard Beaumont; Mohammad Chaudri; René-Jean Dupuy; Frits Hondius; Judge Philip C. Jessup; Joseph Kraft; Pierre Mirel
    - File 6, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 11: 3-6)
      Correspondents include Olajige Aluko; Joseph E. Black; Ursula Braun; Carnegie Endowment (John Goormaghtigh); Yassin El-Ayouty; Martin Ennals; Philip C. Jessup; George Lenczowski; Claude Nigoul; William C. Olson; Prosper Weil
    - File 7, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 12: 1-3)
      Correspondents include Michel Cazenave; Instituto affari internazionali; International Labour Office; International Legal Center (John B. Howard, Howard Larsen); International Peace Academy; J. A. Laponce; Claude Nigoul; Albert Tévoédjrè; Budislav Vukas; Jaroslav Žourek
    - File 8, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 12: 4-6)
      Correspondents include Saad Alfaragi; Driss Guiga; Bruce H. Hasemkamp; International Labour Office (N. Valticos); Philippe Leboulanger; Robert H. Lochner; Claude Nigoul; Jaroslav Žourek
    - File 9, 1973-1976 (Box-folder 12: 7-8, Box-folder 13: 1)
      Correspondents include J. S. Lall; J. A. Laponce; Robert H. Lochner; Henri Michel; Wolfgang Rieger; Daniel Vignes
    - File 10, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 13: 2-4)
      Correspondents include Georges Abi-Saab; Hans Blix; Manuel Diez-Alegria; Axel Edelstam; International Labour Office (Nicolas Valticos); Institut de Droit International; William C. Olson; A. L. Udovitch. Includes reports from the International Commission of Jurists
    - File 11, 1979 (Box-folder 13: 5)
      Correspondents include Carrara Cagni; Bohuslav Chňoupek; Nurettin Karaköylü; and others
  - Cairo University Faculty of Economics and Political Science correspondence and related materials, 1958-1973 (Boxes 13-14)
    - 1958-1973 (Box-folder 13: 6, Box-folder 14: 1-3)
    - 1966-1973 (Box-folder 14: 4-7)
  - Correspondence with students, 1960-1976 (Box-folder 15: 1-4)
  - International Labour Office correspondence, 1970-1977 (Box-folder 15: 5)
  - Socialist unions correspondence and conference materials, 1971-1977 (Boxes 15-16)
    Includes materials from international socialist unions and organizations. Relates in part to Boutros-Ghali's position as an official in the Egyptian Arab Socialist Union and his candidacy in an Egyptian election.
    - 1971-1977 (Box-folder 15: 6-7, Box-folder 16: 1)
    - 1975-1976 (Box-folder 16: 2-3)
    - 1977 (Box-folder 16: 4)
  - International Commission of Jurists, Geneva, correspondence and reports, 1972-1977 (Boxes 16-17)
    - 1972-1973 (Box-folder 16: 5)
    - 1974 (Box-folder 16: 6)
    - 1975-1976 (Box-folder 17: 1)
    - 1975-1977 (Box-folder 17: 2)
  - Writings on relations between the Organization of African Unity and the Arab League, 1974 (Box-folder 17: 3-4)
  - American Foundation (International Legal Center) meeting minutes and correspondence, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 17: 5)
  - University of Khartoum correspondence and related academic materials, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 17: 6, Box-folder 18: 1-2)
  - Instituto affari internazionali (Rome) correspondence, 1974-1977 (Box-folder 18: 3)
  - Pan-African Pugwash Group correspondence and reports, 1976 (Box-folder 18: 4)
  - Lajnat Thawrat 23 Yulyu Sanat 1952 [Committee on Recording the Revolution of 23 July 1952] memoranda, 1976-1977 (Box-folder 18: 5)
    Relates to Boutros-Ghali's membership.
  - "Scientific organizations" correspondence, 1977 (Box-folder 18: 5-6)
    The original Arabic label of this file translates to "scientific organizations," but it actually contains correspondence from international peace research organizations including Instituto Affari Internazionali, Institut de Droit International, Société Française Pour Le Droit International, and International Commission for Jurists.
  - University affairs (University of Jordan), 1977 (Box-folder 18: 7)
- Speeches and Writings, 1950-1998 (Boxes 19-30)
  Includes reprints of journal articles, drafts, manuscripts, and related correspondence. Arranged chronologically.
  - "al-kutal al-dawlīyah fī al-umam Muttahidah," printed copy, 1950s (Box-folder 19: 1)
  - "Le Pacte de l'Atlantique Nord," Revue égyptienne de droit international, printed copy, 1950 (Box-folder 19: 2)
  - "al-atifiqat al-aqlimih al-asiwih" [Asian Regional Agreements], printed copy, 1954 (Box-folder 19: 3)
  - "al-salām al-sūfītī fī urūbā," printed copy, 1954 (Box-folder 19: 4)
  - "fiqdān al'dawih wa jām'h al-dawl al'Arabīyah" [Losing Participation in the Arab League], printed copy, 1955 (Box-folder 19: 5)
  - Mīshāq Sān Salfadūr, printed copy, 1955 (Box-folder 19: 6)
  - "La Ligue Arabe: Notice Bibliographique," Revue égyptienne de droit international, printed copy, 1955 (Box-folder 19: 7)
  - "La Conférence de Bandoeng," Internationales Jahrbuch der Politik, printed copy, 1955 (Box-folder 19: 8)
  - "Versuch einer analyse der panarabischen Bewegung, Internationales Jahrbuch der Politik, printed copy, 1956 (Box-folder 19: 9)
  - [The Rules of Participation in the United Nations], printed copy, 1956 (Box-folder 19: 10)
    Note
    Title translated from original Arabic.
  - "Le Monde Afro-Asiatique et L'AAA," printed copy, 1957 (Box-folder 19: 11)
    Reprint of speech from April 1955.
  - [Economic Importance of the Middle East in International Policy], printed copy, 1958 (Box-folder 19: 12)
  - "Un Precurseur de l'Organisation Internationale: Al Kawakibi," Revue égyptienne de droit international, printed copy, 1960 (Box-folder 19: 13)
  - "Arab Blocs and Western Policy," Internationales Recht und Diplomatie, printed copy (Box-folder 19: 14)
  - [The Principle of Fair Geographical Distribution], printed copy, 1960 (Box-folder 19: 15)
  - [Voting in International Organizations], printed copy, 1961 (Box-folder 19: 16)
  - "Le Principe d'égalité des etats et les organisations internationales," printed copy, 1961 (Box-folder 19: 17)
  - [African Constitutions], printed copy, circa 1962 (Box-folder 19: 18)
  - [Military Alliance and the United Nations], printed copy, 1962 (Box-folder 19: 19)
  - Revision of the articles on the United Nations by Dr. Mohammad Fathallah al-Khatib, 1962 (Box-folder 19: 20)
  - [The Addis Ababa Conference and the Organization of African Unity], printed copy, 1963 (Box-folder 19: 21)
  - [Geographical Areas in Military Alliance], printed copy, 1963 (Box-folder 19: 22)
  - "The Foreign Policy of Egypt," Foreign Policies in a World of Change, printed copy, 1963 (Box-folder 19: 23)
    Physical description
    Photocopy.
  - [Policy of Non-Alignment], printed copy, 1964 (Box-folder 20: 1)
  - "Le Droit à la culture et la declaration universelle des droits de l'homme," Revue égyptienne de droit international, printed copy, 1968 (Box-folder 20: 2)
  - "al-Harakah al-Afrū Āsyawīyah," printed copy, 1969 (Box-folder 20: 3)
  - "L'Organisation de l'unite Africaine et la cooperation economique," Revue égyptienne de droit international, printed copy, 1969 (Box-folder 20: 4)
  - "al-kutal al-ati yumkin etaba'ha letahkik tanfeeth kharar majlis alamin," printed copy, 1971 (Box-folder 20: 5)
  - La Ligue des états Arabes, printed copy, 1972 (Box-folder 20: 6)
  - "En Marge la prochaine conference d'Alger des etats non-alignes," Revue égyptienne de droit international, printed copy, 1973 (Box-folder 20: 7)
  - Dirāsāt fī al-diblūmāsiyah al-'Arabīyah, printed copy, 1973 (Box-folder 20: 8)
  - al-Madkhal fī 'ilm al-siyāsah, printed copy, 1974 (Box-folder 20: 9)
  - Jāmi'at al-Duwal al-'Arabīyah wa-taswīyat al-munāza'āt al-mahallīyah, 1977 (Box-folder 21: 1)
  - Qadāyā 'Arabīyah, 1977 (Box-folder 21: 2)
  - "The Foreign Policy of Egypt in the Post-Sadat Era," Foreign Affairs, 1982 (Box-folder 21: 3)
  - "Mexico y Egipto," speech booklet, 1984 June (Box-folder 21: 4)
  - Address by Boutros Boutros-Ghali at the Eighth Conference of Heads of State or Government of Non-Aligned Countries, Harare, 1986 August-September (Box-folder 21: 5)
  - "Analisis de los Logros Diplomaticos de la Administracion de Mubarak Durant El Ano 1986,", 1987 (Box-folder 21: 6)
  - Will We Survive?, dialogue with Anatoly Gromyko, Robert McNamara, Richard L. Sklar, and Luis Echeverria, Progress Publishers, 1989 (Box-folder 21: 7)
  - "The Future Strategy for the Organization of African Unity and the Non-Alignment Movement," al Siyassa al Dawliyya, printed copy, 1989 October (Box-folder 21: 8)
  - Egypt's Road to Jerusalem: A Diplomat's Story of the Struggle for Peace in the Middle East (Boxes 21-25)
    Early drafts of this book were titled "The Road to Jerusalem." Unless otherwise specified, all drafts are typescript with handwritten notes.
    - Research materials, 1956-1994 (Box-folder 21: 9)
      Includes photocopies of articles on the Middle East by Boutros Boutros-Ghali and others. Also includes notes by Charles Hill and draft of afterword (September 3, 1994).
    - Draft, untitled (second to last chapter), undated (Box-folder 22: 1)
      Handwritten.
    - Draft, 1993 July (Box-folder 22: 2)
      Includes handwritten drafts, research materials, and letter to Saul Bellow.
    - Draft, 1993 August, undated (Box-folder 22: 3)
    - Draft, chapters 1-6, 1994 May 16 (Box-folder 22: 4-5)
    - Draft, chapters 7-10, 1994 June 6-21 (Box-folder 22: 6, Box-folder 23: 1)
      Labeled "Bonne Version."
    - Draft of afterword, 1994 September 3 (Box-folder 23: 2)
    - Draft, chapters 1-11, 1994 December 6 (Box-folder 23: 3-5)
    - Draft, chapters 1-7, 1994 December 6 (Box-folder 23: 6)